[Music]
consider a right triangle with legs of
length a
and b and a hypotenuse of length c
first let's scale this triangle by the
value of c
this creates a right triangle and the
new legs
are length a times c and b times c
the hypotenuse is c squared
next we scale the triangle by the value
of b to obtain another right triangle
this right triangle has leg lengths a
times b and b
squared and a hypotenuse of length c
times b
finally we scale the original triangle
one more time by the value a
this produces a right triangle and in
this instance
the leg lengths are a squared b times a
and hypotenuse ca
notice that the second and third scaled
triangles fit together along their sides
of common length a b
equals b a glued together these
triangles create yet another right
triangle
this can be verified as the two acute
angles are complementary by construction
finally note that this new triangle is
congruent to the first scale triangle as
they have legs of the same lengths and
are both right triangles
therefore the hypotenuses must be equal
so that a squared
plus b squared equals c squared this is
the pythagorean theorem